# Bala Subrahmanyam Varanasi

Email: <u>vabasu@gmail.com</u> Mobile: +919819633692

## Summary

A Senior Software Engineer with more than five years of professional experience from design and document to implementation of various Web and Mobile applications using Python/Django, Ruby on Rails and Android in a fast-paced deadline oriented environments.

### **Technical Skills**

Web Frameworks: Django, Ruby on Rails and Flask. Programming Languages: Python, Ruby and Java Scripting Languages: Python, Ruby and JavaScript Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL and MongoDB Cloud Platforms: Amazon AWS and Digital Ocean

CI/CD Tools: Jenkins, Ansible and Docker.

Markup Languages: HTML5, Markdown and reStructuredText

Operating systems: Ubuntu and Mac OS

**Mobile Development:** Android

JavaScript Libraries: ¡Query, BackboneJs (Basic), KnockoutJS (Basic), ReactJS (Basic)

#### **Interests**

Team Building, Product Development, Digital Media Marketing, Web Development, Mobile Development, OpenSource Software and DevOps

## **Experience**

# Senior Software Engineer at Glitterbug Technology, November 2015 - Present

- Build scalable software through architecture discussions with the leadership
- Participate with other teams, to provide solutions for our customers
- Manage Sprint/Development cycle for the development team and manage team during the cycle
- Determine complexity level of a story in a Sprint/Development cycle
- Communicate with leadership on current project status
- Error prevention and error detection possible
- Continuous integration
- Test-driven development
- Roundup or Track for bug tracking and project management

#### Software Engineer at TinyOwl Technology, April 2015 – November 2015

Responsible for developing and maintaining micro service applications using Ruby On Rails, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Redis, AWS and etc...

#### Founder at Firebolt Labs, Aug 2014 – April 2015

Headed the day-to-day-operations, as well as handled the company's product and consulting projects.

## Software Developer at Crypsis Technologies, Sept 2013 - July 2014

Responsible for the development of web and mobile apps using various technologies like Ruby on Rails, Android and NodeJS.

## Intern and Software Developer at Agiliq Info Solutions, Dec 2011 – Aug 2013

Worked with several clients across the globe on various projects and helped them in building various web and mobile apps using Python/Django and Android.

# **Projects**

#### **Django Applications**

- CoverFox Insurance, an online insurance destination.
- <u>Sufo</u>, an Educational Video site for Physicians.
- Feature Developments in <u>Suggestar</u>.
- Customized the Django Admin CMS for <u>CineSport</u>, an innovative web video syndication company.
- Feature Development in <u>TravelDojo</u>, a company to create travel guides to the Southeast Asia region.
- Testing and Bugfixes Ocassio Health Strategies.
- Seeded HyderabadWiki with Wikipedia dump in LocalWiki Format.
- The Xaming Arena, a simple Online Examination system using Django framework.

### **Ruby on Rails Applications**

- <u>TinyOwl</u>, a food ordering application.
- Mr Delicious, an online food delivery system.
- <u>Investment Club</u> by <u>StockViews</u>.
- Feature Development in <u>Swym</u>.
- <u>Virtual Analyst</u> by <u>Analytics Intelligence</u>.
- Feature Developments and Test Cases Development in Mega Golf Virtual League.

# **Android Applications**

- "Windows Ambassador", an application by Microsoft.
- "Where's My App?", checks the availability status of apps and games in the Windows Phone Store.
- "Baby Names", a simple android app to choose a baby name.

## **Open Source**

- Feature Development in django-graphos.
- Bugfixes and pep8 improvements in scikit-learn.
- pep8 improvements in joblib.
- <u>Sentiment Analyzer</u>, a simple sentiment classification tool for Telugu Language.
- Feature Improvements and Test Cases in Join.agiliq.com
- Improvments to code samples in DjenOfDjango.

## **Publications**

"Python Requests Essentials", a book which showcases fundamental as well as advanced Python Requests concepts. (ISBN-10: 1784395412) (ISBN-13: 978-1784395414)

#### Education

- Artificial Intelligence Nanodegree, Udacity, January 2017 Present.
- **Batchelor of Technology**, Information Technology from Vishnu Institute of Technology, 2008 2012.
- **Intermediate Education** from Santhiniketan Junior College, 2006 2008.
- SSC from G.V&K.B.M School, 2006.

# As a Speaker

PyCon India, 2013; SciPy 2011 & 2013 and CoDec 2012.